We're almost at the end of this routing module, a lot of content was covered here.
Bu ynlendirme bitiminde neredeyse imkanszd Martal, burada ok sayda ierik kaplyd.
Now there's one important thing you have to know regarding routing when using the react router, when
imdi, kullanrken rota hakknda bilmeniz gereken nemli bir husus, uygulamanzda gerek bir sunucuya gelen
it comes to deploying your app to a real server because you won't notice it here on the development
poloya gelince ynlendirici tepki veriyor nk burada zaten doru ekilde yaplandrlm olduu
server because it's already configured correctly.
iin gelitirme sunucusunda bunu fark etmeyeceksiniz.
You have to remember how handling requests actually works in the web.
Tama taleplerinin aslnda web'de nasl ilediini hatrlamak zorundasnz.
We have the user who sends a request to the server and we have our react app which is then loaded on
Sunucuya bir istek gnderen kullanc sahibiyiz ve daha sonra indeks HVM edinme sayfasnda ykl olan
the index.html page.
yeniden eyleme geme uygulamamz var.
The thing is before we load to index.html page the server needs to find out which page the user actually
h e-posta sayfasna yklemeden nce sunucunun kullancnn hangi sayfay ziyaret etmek istediini renmesi gerekiyor.
wanted to visit.
ncelikle, index
That of course is the case because the server always handles requests first,
Tabii ki durum byle, nk sunucu her zaman ilk istekleri ilemektedir.
this is how the Internet works.
nternet nasl iliyor byle.
The problem is it's the react app which knows the routes.
Sorun, rotalar bilen Riak olmas.
So if we visit /posts, there is no /posts route on our server, that is defined in the javascript
Bylece, eik yazlara bakarsak, sunucumuzda hibir zaman alamadmz dizin HTL sayfasnda yklenen javascript kodunda
code which is loaded on the index.html page which we never get because we get a 404 error on the
tanmlanan kesme iareti yolu yoktur nk sunucuda hata iin 4 0 alacamz umduk
server because we tried to visit a route which is unknown to the server.
nk Sunucu tarafndan bilinmeyen bir rota.
And clearly this is not what you saw during development because as I said the development server is
grdnz bu deil nk nk gelitirme sunucusu zaten doru yaplandrlm dedi.
already configured correctly.
Ve akas gelime srasnda
We have to configure the server in a way that it always forwards requests no matter if it understands
Sunucuyu, isteklerini anlayan veya yapmasn her zaman isteklerini n plana karacak ekilde
them or not,
yaplandrmamz gerekir.
so also 404 error requests to the client, so that it always returns the index.html page, also
Ayn zamanda hataya veya istemciye olan talepler iin, indeks ekibi l sayfasn da, bilinen istekler
for unknown requests because this then allows react to take over and parse the request against the
iin de dndrr, nk bu daha sonra bildikleri yollara kar talebi devralmaya ve ayrtrmaya
routes it knows.
izin verir.
So we should always load index.html
Bu yzden hep indeks H'yi yklemeliyiz. T. Ve eer o zaman bir istek var bilmiyoruz.
and if then there is a request we dont know,
yi 4 ynlendirici ile hatalar iin nasl baa kacanz rendiniz.
well you learned how to handle 404 errors with the react router.
imdi dediim gibi, burada kullandmz gelitirme sunucusu
Now as I said, the development server we used here already is configured to always load the index.html
her zaman gelecek ya ekibi dosyasn ykleyecek ekilde yaplandrlmtr.
file.
Bu, kendi sunucunuzda uygulamay barndrrken de yapmanz gereken bir eydir.
It is something you will also have to do when hosting the app on your own server though,
Her zaman bir sonraki HVM cihazna geri dnn.
always return index.html
Hata durumlarnda bile ve zellikle 4 0'da.
even and especially in 404 error cases.
Uygulamanz sunucunuzda barndrrken farknda olmak zorunda olduunuz baka bir ey var.
There is another thing you have to be aware of when hosting your app on your server,
Eer ev sahiplii yapyorsa, rneklenmi nokta com hibir ey izgiyi diyelim diyelim.
if you are hosting it on let's say example.com/
eik izgiyle aaya kaydrn klasr tepki vermelisiniz.
so if that's the page with which we're landing on the root page of your react app, you don't need to
Bu, tepki uygulamanzn gzergah sayfasnda yer aldm sayfaysa, zel bir
set up anything special. But if you're serving your app from let's say example.com/myapp, so
ey ayarlamanza gerek yoktur; ancak, uygulamanz sunuyorsanz, rnein unu diyelim ki, com, uygulamanz
anything beneath that folder should be your react app,
Bunu yeniden davranmasn syle.
you need to tell react about this,
Ynlendiricinin hassas olmasn salyorsun.
the react router to be precise.
Tepki ynlendirici iin
You need to set the base path for the react router and I want to quickly show you how to do that. In your
dayana ayarlamanz gerekir ve bunu uygulamanzda nasl yapacanz hzl bir ekilde gstermek istiyorum.
application,
Tarayc ynlendiricisini kullandnz yerde.
in the place where you use browser router,
ve gerekten bunu yapmak gerekir.
so in our case in the app.js file here browser router, you can also configure that and you really
Dolaysyla bizim durumumuzda ve o aslnda dosyay burada tarayc ynlendirici de yaplandrabilir
need to do that.
Ancak ayarlayabileceiniz bir basename pervanesi var ve varsaylan olarak eik izgi olarak ayarlanmtr.
But there is a base name prop you can set and by default, that's set to slash.
Varsaylan budur, ancak ayarlamanza gerek yoktur.
So this is the default which you don't need to set.
Uygulamanz uygulamamdan sunuyorsanz, bunu
If your serving your app from myapp, you should set this to /myapp, then all your requests are
uygulamanz kesmek iin ayarlamanz gerekiyorsa, tm istekleriniz uygulama izikimine ve ardndan iaret ettiiniz balantya ynlendirilir.
routed against myapp/ and then the link you were pointing to.
Aksi halde burada bir banz olsayd.
Otherwise, if you had a link like here,
Buraya gnderiyi tkladnzda sayfa deiikliini
if you push the page change up on clicking a post, here we navigate to /posts and it would always
yukar iterseniz, eik yazlara gidersek, bunu daima kk alannza ekleriz.
add this to your root domain.
imdi, yeniden uygulama olsayd, uygulamann
Now if your react app is served from /myapp, it will only work correctly and add it to the
ba harflerinden sunulur, ancak yalnzca dzgn ekilde alr ve alan adnzn sonuna ekleyerek uygulamanmn ba harfini keser.
end of your domain /myapp
Eer bazename ayarlanmsa, uygulamanza bir alt dizinden hizmet verirken basename ayarladnzdan emin olun.
If basename is set up. So whenever you are serving your app from a sub directory, make sure to set basename.
Yani burada basename'yi kaldracam ya da oaltlr ve burada
So here I will remove basename or I'll duplicate it and comment it out to leave it here for reference and
referans olarak brakp taraycdan kaldrmak iin yorum yaparm.
remove it in the browser route
Aslnda kullanyoruz Ama bu senin bilmen gereken bir ey.